NATHAN D. MILES

RESEARCH INTERESTS

Compact objects and accretion phenomena; space weather and its effects on the geomagnetic environment; big data and machine learning

CARRER OBJECTIVES

To become a NASA astronaut serving as a mission specialist in the Lunar Gateway program by providing expertise in space weather and radiation from both solar particles and galactic cosmic rays.

To serve as an advocate for the advancement of science and science education in the United States of America by stressing the importance of international collaboration in solving global problems shared by all of humanity.

EDUCATION

B.S. Astronomy, Summa Cum Laude

August 2010 - 2015

Department of Astronomy University of Florida

B.S. Physics, Cum Laude

August 2010 - 2015

Department of Physics University of Florida

B.S. Mathematics, Cum Laude

August 2010 - 2015

Department of Mathematics University of Florida

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Red Canyon Engineering & Software, Cape Canaveral, Florida June 2015 - September 2015 KLXS-II Intern

As a Kennedy LX Support Contract II intern, I developed a touch screen interface and weather app that interfaced with the GlassWall project using the game engine, Unity. The GUI interface was written in C# while the weather was programmatically queried from the Dark Sky API.

Red Canyon Engineering & Software, Cape Canaveral, Florida October 2015 - June 2016 Software Engineer

As a software engineer I supported various investigate projects led by the Project Management Office at Kennedy Space Center. In addition to the projects I supported, I was also the principle investigator of the Lightning Prediction and Warning System (LPAWS) funded through the 2016 Kennedy Space Center Kickstart Competition.

Space Telescope Science Institute, Baltimore, Maryland

June 2016 - May 2018

Research and Instrument Analyst I

As a Research and Instrument Analyst I on the Advanced Camera for Surveys (ACS) Instrument Team I was tasked with the following duties and roles:

- Create and deliver superdark and superbias reference files each month.
- Principle Investigator of the ACS Postflash Calibration program.
- Interface with Exposure Time Calculator Software Team as the Instruments Divisions Coordination rep for ACS.
- Update and enhance the ACS Website to provide ACS users with a more intuitive user experience.
- Provide user support through the ACS Help Desk.
- Analyze regression suites to ensure updates made to the ACS calibration software are correctly implemented and satisfy requirements.
- Provide science support to Dr. Ori Fox following an assignment by the Technical Staff Research Committee.

Space Telescope Science Institute, Baltimore, Maryland

May 2018 - Present

Research and Instrument Analyst II

As a Research and Instrument Analyst II on the Advanced Camera for Surveys (ACS) Instrument Team I was tasked with following duties and roles:

- Provide user support through the ACS Help Desk and triaging of general HST Help tickets.
- Mentor junior staff through the Instrument Division's Mentoring program.
- Update the Technical Staff Training Guide with supplemental information concerning alternatives for parallelizing python code.
- Interface with Science Calibration Software Branch (SCSB) to help resolve outstanding issues, implement new logic, and fix bugs in ACS calibration pipelines, as well as, review and approve all updates made to the ACSTOOLS python package.
- Oversee and help manage the migration of the entire ACS website from a Zope based CMS to Jahia based CMS while modernizing the website along the way
- Provide science support to Dr. Susana Deustua and Dr. Gonzalo Tancredi following an assignment by the Technical Staff Research Committee.

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

Space Telescope Science Institute, Baltimore, Maryland

June 2017 - March 2018

HST FUV/NUV Photometry of the Putative Binary Companion to the SN 1993J Progentior

Advisor: Dr. Ori D. Fox

As part of the Technical Staff at the Space Telescope Science institute I was awarded research time to perform data reduction and analysis of WFC3/UVIS and ACS/SBC observations from HST GO Proposal 13648. We found strong evidence consistent with previous analyses of the existence of a surviving B-type companion and the results were presented at the 232nd meeting of the American Astronomical Society. However, with a lack of contemporaneous optical photometry there is insufficient data to constrain circumstellar interactions and so the results remain unpublished pending further analysis.

Skills Acquired

- Source finding and deblending (SExtractor).
- Iterative PSF building via minimization of aperture photometry and PSF photometry residuals for bright isolated sources (Pyraf, DAOPHOT).
- PSF photometry of crowded sources and pipeline processing

Geophysics with Hubble Space Telescope

Advisors: Dr. Susana Deustua and Dr. Gonzalo Tancredi

As part of the Technical Staff at the Space Telescope Science institute I was awarded research time to perform data reduction and analysis for HST AR Proposal 14587. I wrote the entire data analysis package from scratch (> 6000 lines of code) to download, process, and analyze over 75,000 dark calibration frames taken with 5 different CCD imagers. Using statistics generated by the pipeline we were able to independently confirm thickness models for ACS/WFC, ACS/HRC, WFC3/UVIS. We were also able to demonstrate the well-known anti-correlation between solar activity and observed cosmic ray rate.

Skills Acquired

- Cloud processing with AWS and the HST public dataset.
- End-to-end pipeline processing including all necessary documentation using ReadTheDocs.
- Machine learning (binary classification using KNearestNeighbors algorithm)
- Big data analysis (4.5 TB worth of images analyzed, over 1.2 billion cosmic rays studied)
- Parallel processing with dask

TECHNICAL SKILLS

Software Languages

BASH, C++, python (preferred), HTML

Modeling and Data Analysis

astropy, DAOPHOT, numpy, pandas, photutils, scipy, scikit-learn, scikit-image

Data Visualization

matplotlib, plotly

Website Frameworks

flask, jinja

Parallelization

dask, multiprocessing

Version Control

git

PUBLICATIONS

Technical Reports

- 1. N.D. Miles, Updates to Post-Flash Calibration for the Advanced Camera for SurveysWide Field Channel. ACS ISR 2018-03. Space Telescope Science Institute, March 2018.
- 2. T.D. Desjardins, **N. D. Miles**, J. E. Ryon, D. C. Borncamp, *ACS/WFC Superbias, Superdark, and Sink Pixel File Generation*. ACS TIR 2018-01. Space Telescope Science Institute, August 2018.
- 3. N.D. Miles, P. L. Lim, A. Bellini, N.A. Grogin, *Updates to the CALACS Cosmic Ray Rejection Routine: ACSREJ.* ACS ISR 2018-05. Space Telescope Science Institute, September 2018.

Conference Abstracts

- 1. N.D. Miles, N.A. Grogin, (2018), Calibration Improvements for the Hubble Space Telescope Advanced Camera for Surveys Wide Field Channel: Post-Flash and Commanding Overheads. American Astronomical Society Meeting Abstracts, 231, #355.33
- N.D. Miles, O.D. Fox, K.A. Bostroem, W. Zheng, M. Graham, S. D. Van Dyk, A.V. Filippenko, T. Matheson, V. Dwarkadas, C. Fransson, N. Smith, T. Brink, (2018), HST FUV/NUV Photometry of the Putative Binary Companion to the SN 1993J Progenitor. American Astronomical Society Meeting Abstracts, 232, #320.09
- 3. S. Deustua, N. D. Miles, G. Tancredi, (2018), Geophysics with the Hubble Space Telescope, Abstract GP13A-41, presented at 2018 AGU Fall Meeting, Washington, D.C., 10-14 Dec.